CHAPTER 4 MARTHA When she opened her eyes in the morning it was because a young housemaid
had come into her room to light the fire and was kneeling on the Hearth rug
raking out the cinders noisily. Mary lay and watched her for a
few moments and then began to look about the room. She had never seen a room at
all like it and thought it curious and gloomy but The walls were covered with
tapestry with a forest scene embroidered on it. There were fantastically dressed
people under the trees and in the distance there was a glimpse of the
turrets of a castle. There were hunters and horses and dogs and
ladies. Mary felt as if she were in the forest with them. Out of a deep window
she could see a great climbing stretch of land which seemed to have no trees on
it, and to look rather like an endless, dull, purplish sea. "What is that?" she said,
pointing out of the window. Martha, the young housemid who had just risen to her
feet, looked and pointed also. "That there?" she said.
"Yes." "That's the more with a good-natured grin. "Does thou like it?" "No," answered Mary.
"I hate it." "That's because that not used to it," Martha said, going back to her heart
th thinks it's too big and bare now. But thou will like it." "Do you?" inquired Mary I
that I do," answered Martha, cheerfully polishing away at the grate. "I just love
it. It's none bare. It's covered with growing things as smells sweet. It's fair
lovely in spring and summer when the gors and broom and Heathers in flow It
smells a honey and there's such a lot of fresh air and the sky looks so high and
the bees and skylarks make such a nice noise humming and singing ah I wouldn't
live away from the mo for anything Mary listened to her with a grave, puzzled
expression. The native servants she had been used to in India were not in the
least like this. They were obsequious and servile and did not presume to talk to
their masters as if they were their equals. They made salams and called them
"protector of the poor" and names of that sort. Indian servants were commanded to do things, not
asked. It was not the custom to say "please" and "thank you" and Mary had always
slapped her a in the face when she was angry. She wondered a little what this
girl would do if one slapped her in the face. She was a round, rosy, good-natured
looking creature, but she had a sturdy way which made Mistress Mary wonder if
she might not even slap back— —if the person who slapped her was only a
little girl. "You are a strange servant," she said from her pillows, rather holy
Martha sat up on her heels, with her blacking brush in her hand, and laughed,
without seeming the least out of temper. "Eh! I know that," she said. "If there
was a grand Ms at mistle I should never have been even one of the under
housemaids. I might have been L to be skullery maid but I'd never have been
let set upstairs I'm too common and I talk too much
Yorkshire. But this is a funny house for all it's so grand. Seems like there's
neither Master nor Mistress except Mr.
Pitcher and Mrs.
Medlock. Mr. Craven, he won't be troubled about anything when he's here and he's nearly always
away. Mrs. Medlock gave me the place out of kindness. She told me she could never
have done it if mwe had been like other big houses." "Are you going to be my servant?"
Mary asked, still in her imperious little Indian way. Martha began to rub her great
again. "I'm Mrs. Medlock's servant," she said stoutly and she's Mr
Craven but I'm to do the housemaid's work up here and wait on you a bit. But
you won't need much waiting on." "Who is going to dress me?" demanded
Mary. Martha sat up on her heels again and stared. She spoke in broad Yorkshire
in her amazement Canada dress thy s she said. "What do you mean? I don't understand
your language," said Mary hey I forgot," Martha said. "Mrs.
Medlock told me I'd have to be careful or you wouldn't know what I was saying I
mean can't you put on your own clothes?" "No," answered Mary, quite
indignantly. "I never did in my life. My eye had addressed me, of
course." "Well," said Martha, evidently not in the least aware that she was
impudent, "it's time thou should learn thou cannot begin younger. It'll do thee
good to wait on thy s a bit. My mother always said she couldn't see why grand
people's children didn't turn out fair fools— —what with nurses and being washed
and dressed and took out to walk as if they was puppies!" "It is different in India," said
Mistress Mary disdainfully. She could scarcely stand this. But Martha was not at all
crushed a I can see it's different," she answered almost
sympathetically. "I dare say it's because there's such a lot of blacks there
instead of respectable white people. When I heard you was coming from India I
thought you was a black too." Mary sat up in bed
furious. "What!" she said. "What! You thought I was a native. You— —you daughter of a pig!"
Martha stared and looked hot. "Who are you calling names?" she
said. "You needn't be so vexed. That's not the way for a young lady to talk. I've
nothing against the blacks. When you read about them in tracks they're always very
religious. You always read as a black's a man and a brother. I've never seen a
black and I was fair pleased to think I was going to see one close. When I come
in to light your fire this morning I crept up to your bed and pulled the
cover back careful to look at you and there you was,"
disappointedly, "no more black than me— —for all you're so yellow Mary did not even
try to control her rage and humiliation. "You thought I was a native!
You dared! You don't know anything about natives! They are not people— —they're
servants who must Salam to you. You know nothing about India. You know nothing
about anything!" She was in such a rage and felt so helpless before the girl's
simple stare, and somehow she suddenly felt so horribly lonely and far away
from everything she understood and which understood her, that she threw herself
face downward on the pillows and burst into passionate sobbing. She sobbed so
unrestrainedly that good-natured Yorkshire Martha was a little frightened
and quite quite sorry for her. She went to the bed and bent over her he you
mustn't cry like that there!" she begged.
"You mustn't for sure. I didn't know you'd be vexed. I don't know anything about
anything just like you said. I beg your pardon, Miss. Do stop
crying There was something comforting and really friendly in her queer
Yorkshire speech and sturdy way which had had a good effect on Mary. She
gradually ceased crying and became quiet.
Martha looked relieved. "It's time for thee to get up
now," she said. "Mrs. Medlock said I was to carry that breakfast and tea and dinner
into the room next to this. It's been made into a nursery for thee. I'll help
thee on with thy clothes if thou get out of bed. If the buttons are at the back
thou cannot button them up thyself When Mary at last decided deed
to get up, the clothes Martha took from the wardrobe were not the ones she had
worn when she arrived the night before with Mrs.
Medlock. "Those are not mine," she said. "Mine are black." She looked the thick white
wool coat and dress over, and added with cool approval: "Those are nicer than
mine." "These are the ones they must put on," Martha answered. "Mr. Craven ordered Mrs. Medlock
to get him in London. He said 'I won't have a child
dressed in black wandering about like a lost soul,' he said it would make the
place sadder than it is. Put color on her.'
Mother she said she knew what he meant.
Mother always knows what a body means.
She doesn't hold with black herself I hate black things," said Mary.
The dressing process was one which taught them both something. Martha had
"buttoned up" her little sisters and brothers but she had never seen a child
who stood still and waited for another person to do things for her as if she
had neither hands nor feet of her own. "Why doesn't that put on th own shoes?"
she said when Mary quietly held out her foot. "My a did it," answered Mary, staring.
"It was the custom." She said that very often—" —"It was the
custom." The native servants were always saying it.
If one told them to do a thing their ancestors had not done for a thousand
years they gazed at one mildly and said, "It is not the custom" and one knew
that was the end of the matter. It had not been the custom that
Mistress Mary should do anything but stand and allow herself to be dressed
like a doll, but before she was ready for breakfast she began to suspect that her
life at mlethwa Manor would end by teaching her a number of things quite
new to her— —things such as putting on her own shoes and stockings, and picking up
things she let fall. If Martha had been a well-trained fine young lady's maid she would have
been more subservient and respectful and would have known that it
was her business to brush hair, and button boots, and pick things up and lay
them away. She was, however, only an untrained Yorkshire rustic who who had
been brought up in a Morland cottage with a swarm of little brothers and
sisters who had never dreamed of doing anything but waiting on themselves and
on the younger ones who were either babies in arms or just learning to
totter about and tumble over things. If Mary Lennox had been a child who was
ready to be amused she would perhaps have laughed at Martha's readiness to
talk, but Mary only listened to her coldly and wondered at her freedom of
manner. At first she was not at all interested, but gradually, as the girl
rattled on in her good-tempered, homely way, Mary began to notice what she was
saying hey you should see them all," she said. "There's 12 of us and my father only
gets 16 shilling a week. I can tell you my mother's put to it to get porridge
for a allall They tumble about on the Moore and play there all day and mother
says the air of the Moore fattens them She says she believes they eat the grass
same as the wild ponies do. Our Dickon, he's 12 years old and he's got a young
pony he calls his own." "Where did he get it?" asked
Mary. "He found it on the mall with its mother when it was a little one and he
began to make friends with it and give it bits of bread and pluck young grass
for for it. And it got to like him so it
follows him about and it lets him get on its back. Dickon's a kind lad and animals
likes him." Mary had never possessed an animal pet of her own and had always
thought she should like one. So she began to feel a slight interest in Dickon, and
as she had never before been interested in anyone but herself, it was the dawning of a healthy
sentiment. When she went into the room which had been made into a nursery for her,
she found that it was rather like the one she had slept in. It was not a
child's room, but a grownup person's room, with gloomy old pictures on the walls
and heavy old oak chairs. A table in the center was set with a good substantial
breakfast. But she had always had a very small appetite, and she looked with
something more than indifference at the first plate Martha set before her. "I
don't want it," she said thou doesn't want thy porridge!" Martha exclaimed
incredulously. "No th doesn't know how good it is. Put a bit of trial on it or a
bit of sugar." "I don't want it," repeated Mary he said Martha. "I can't abide to see
good vials go to waste. If our children was at this table they'd clean it bare
in 5 minutes." "Why?" said Mary coldly. "Why!" echoed Martha. "Because they
scarce ever had their stomachs full in their lives. They're as hungry as young hawks and
foxes." "I don't know what it is to be hungry," said Mary, with the indifference
of ignorance. Martha looked indignant. "Well, it would do thee good to
try it. I can see that plain enough," she said outspokenly. "I've no patience with folus
sits and just stares at good bread and meat. My word! don't I wish Dickon and
Phil and Jane and the rest of them had what's here under their pin
fores Why don't you take it to them?"
suggested Mary. "It's not mine," answered Martha stoutly and this isn't my day out. I get
my day out once a month same as the rest.
Then I go home and clean up for mother and give her a day's rest." Mary drank
some tea and ate a little toast and some marmalade. "You wrap up warm and run out
and play you," said Martha. "It'll do you good and give you some stomach for your
meat." Mary went to the window. There were gardens and paths and big trees, but
everything looked dull and wintry. "Out? Why should I go out on a day like
this?" "Well, if thou doesn't go out th'll have to stay in and what has thou got to
do?" Mary glanced about her. There was nothing to do. When Mrs. Medlock had prepared the
nursery she had not thought of amusement. Perhaps it would be better to
go and see what the gardens were like. "Who will go with me?" she inquired. Martha
stared. "You'll go by yourself," she answered. "You'll have to learn to play
like other children does when they haven't got sisters and
brothers. Our Dickon goes off on the mo by him himself and plays for
hours. That's how he made friends with the pony. He's got sheep on the moall
that knows him and birds as comes and eats out of his
hand. However little there is to eat, he always saves a bit of his bread to coax his
pets." It was really this mention of Dickon which made Mary decide to go out,
though she was not aware of it. There would be birds outside though there
would not be ponies or sheep. They would be different from the birds in India and
it might amuse her to look at them.
Martha found her coat and hat for her and a pair of stout little boots and she
showed her her way downstairs If that goes around that way
they'll come to the gardens," she said, pointing to a gate in a wall of
shrubbery. "There's lots of flowers in summertime but there's nothing blooming
now." She seemed to hesitate a second before she added, "One of the gardens is
locked up. No one has been in it for 10 years." "Why?" asked Mary in spite of
herself. Here was another locked door added to the hundred in the strange
house. "Mr. Craven had it shut when his wife died so sudden. He won't let no one
go inside. It was her garden. He locked the door and dug a hole and buried the
key. There's Mrs. Medlock's bell ringing— —I must run." After she was gone Mary turned
down the walk which led to the door in the shrubbery. She could not help
thinking about the garden which no one had been into for 10
years. She wondered what it would look like and whether there were any flowers still alive in
it. When she had passed through the shrubbery gate she found herself in
great gardens, with wide lawns and winding walks with clipped borders.
There were trees, and flower beds and evergreens clipped into strange shapes,
and a large pool with an old gray fountain in its midst. But the flower
beds were bare and wintry and the fountain was not playing. This was not the garden which
was shut up. How could a garden be shut up? You could always walk into a garden.
She was just thinking this when she saw that, at the end of the path she was
following, there seemed to be a long wall, with ivy growing over
it. She was not familiar enough with England to know that she was coming upon
the kitchen Gardens where the vegetables and fruit were growing. She went toward the wall and
found that there was a green door in the ivy, and that it stood
open. This was not the closed garden, evidently, and she could go into
it. She went through the door and found that it was a garden with walls all
around it and that it was only one of several walled gardens which seemed to
open into one another. She saw another open green door, revealing bushes and
pathways between beds containing winter vegetables fruit trees were trained flat
against the wall, and over some of the beds there were glass
frames. The place was bare and ugly enough, Mary thought, as she stood and stared about her.
It might be nicer in summer when things were green, but there was nothing pretty about it
now. Presently an old man with a spade over his shoulder walked through the
door leading from the second garden. He looked startled when he saw Mary, and
then touched his cap. He had a sirly old face, and did not seem at all pleased to
see her— —but then she was displeased with his garden and wore her "quite contrary"
expression, and certainly did not seem at all pleased to see him. "What is this
place?" she asked. "One of the kitchen Gardens he answered. "What is that?" said
Mary, pointing through the other green door. "Another of them shortly. "There's
another on T side of the wall and there's the orchard to side of
that." "Can I go in them?" asked Mary. "If thou likes. But there's not to see."
Mary made no response. She went down the path and through the second green
door. There she found more walls and winter vegetables and glass
frames, but in the second wall there was another green door and it was not
open. Perhaps it led into the garden which no one had seen for 10 years. As
she was not at all a timid child and always did what she wanted to do, Mary
went to the green door and turned the handle. She hoped the door would not open
because she wanted to be sure she had found the mysterious
garden— —but it did open quite easily and she walked through it and found herself in an
orchard. There were walls all around it also and trees trained against them, and
there were bare fruit trees growing in the winter brown
grass— —but there was no green door to be seen anywhere. Mary looked for it, and yet when
she had entered the upper end of the garden she had noticed that the wall did
not seem to end with the orchard but to extend beyond it as if it enclosed a
place at the other side. She could see the tops of trees
above the wall, and when she stood still she saw a bird with a bright red breast
sitting on the topmost branch of one of them, and suddenly he burst into his winter song—
—almost as if he had caught sight of her and was calling to
her. She stopped and listened to him and somehow his cheerful, friendly little
whistle gave her a pleased feeling— —even a disagreeable little girl may be lonely,
and the big closed house and big bare Moore and big bare gardens had made this
one feel as if there was no one left in the world but
herself. If she had been an affectionate child, who had been used to being loved, she
would have broken her heart, but even though she was "Mistress Mary Quite
Contrary" she was desolate, and the bright breasted little bird brought a look into
her sour little face which was almost a smile. She listened to him until he flew
away. He was not like an Indian bird and she liked him and wondered if she should
ever see him again perhaps he lived in the mysterious garden and knew all about
it. Perhaps it was because she had nothing whatever to do that she thought
so much of the deserted garden. She was curious about it and wanted to see what it was
like. Why had Mr archal Craven buried the key? If he had liked his wife so much why
did he hate her garden? She wondered if she should ever
see him, but she knew that if she did she should not like him, and he would not
like her, and that she should only stand and stare at him and say nothing, though
she should be wanting dreadfully to ask him why he had done such a queer
thing. "People never like me and I never like people," she thought. "And I never can
talk as the Crawford children could. They were always talking and laughing and making
noises." She thought of the robin and of the way he seemed to sing his song at
her, and as she remembered the treetop he perched on she stopped rather suddenly
on the path. "I believe that tree was in the secret garden— —I feel sure it was," she
said. "There was a wall around the place and there was no
door." She walked back into the first kitchen Garden she had entered and found
the old man digging there. She went and stood beside him and watched him a few
moments in her cold little way. He took no notice of her and so at
last she spoke to to him. "I have been into the other gardens," she said. "There
was nothing to prevent thee," he answered crusty I went into the
orchard." "There was no dog at the door to bite thee," he answered. "There was no door
there into the other garden," said Mary.
"What garden?" he said in a rough voice, stopping his digging for a moment. "The
one on the other side of the wall," answered Mistress Mary. "There are trees
there— —I saw the tops of them. A bird with
a red breast was sitting on one of them and he sang." To her surprise the sirly old
weather-beaten face actually changed its expression. A slow smile spread over it
and the gardener looked quite different.
It made her think that it was curious how much nicer a person looked when he
smiled. She had not thought of it before. He turned about to the orchard
side of his garden and began to whistle— —a low soft whistle. She could not
understand how such a surly man could make such a coaxing
sound. Almost the next moment a wonderful thing happened. She heard a soft little
rushing flight through the air— —and it was the bird with the red breast flying
to them, and he actually a lighted on the big CLA of earth quite near to the
gardener's foot here Here he is," chuckled the old man, and then he spoke to the
bird as if he was speaking to a child. "Where is thou be th cheeky little
beggar?" he said. "I've not seen thee before today hast thou begun that courting this
early in the season that too
forward The bird put his tiny head on one side and looked up at him with his
soft bright eye which was like a black DW drop He seemed quite familiar and not the least
afraid. He hopped about and pecked the earth briskly, looking for seeds and
insects. It actually gave Mary a queer feeling in her heart, because he was so
pretty and cheerful and seemed so like a person. He had a tiny plump body and a
delicate beak, and slender delicate legs Will he always come when you call him?"
she asked almost in a whisper I that he will. I've knowed him ever since he was a
fledgling. He come out of the nest in the other garden and when first he flew over
the wall he was too weak to fly back for a few days and we got
friendly. When he went over the wall again the rest of the brood was gone and
he was lonely and he come back to me." "What kind of a bird is he?" Mary asked.
"Doesn't th no He's a Robbin red breast and they're the friendliest curious
birds alive. They're almost as friendly as dogs— —if you know how to get on with
them Watch him pecking about there and looking round at us now and again. He
knows we're talking about him." It was the queerest thing in the world to see the
old fellow. He looked at the plump little Scarlet waist coated bird as if he were
both proud and fond of him. "He's a conceited one," he chuckled. "He likes to
hear folk talk about him and curious— —bless me, there never was his like for
curiosity and meddling He's always coming to see what I'm planting He knows
all the things Mr Craven never troubles his cell to find out. He's the head gardener, he
is." The robin hopped about busily pecking the soil and now and then stopped and
looked at them a little. Mary thought his black DW drop eyes gazed at her with great
curiosity. It really seemed as if were finding out all about her. The queer feeling in her heart
increased. "Where did the rest of the brood fly to?" she asked. "There's no knowing The old ones
turn them out of their nest and make them fly and they're scattered before
you know it. This one was a knowing one and he knew he was
lonely." Mistress Mary went a step nearer to the robin and looked at him very hard.
"I'm lonely," she said. She had not known before that this
was one of the things which made her feel sour and
cross. She seemed to find it out when the robin looked at her and she looked at
the robin. The old gardener pushed his cap back on his bald head and stared at her a
minute. "Art thou the little wench from India?" he asked. Mary nodded. "Then no wonder th
lonely th be loner before th's done," he said. He began to dig again, driving his
spade deep into the rich black garden soil while the robin hopped about very busily
employed. "What is your name?" Mary inquired.
He stood up to answer her. "Ben weather staff he answered, and then he added with
a sirly chuckle, "I'm lonely myself except when he's with me," and he jerked his
thumb toward the robin he the only friend I've got." "I have no friends at all,"
said Mary. "I never had. My a didn't like me and I never played with
anyone It is a Yorkshire habit to say what you think with blunt frankness an
old Ben weather staff was a Yorkshire Moore man th and me are a good bit alike," he
said. "We was Wo out of the same cloth.
We're neither of us goodlooking and we're both of us as sour as we look.
We've got the same nasty tempers, both of us, I'll warrant." This was plain speaking, and Mary
Lennox had never heard the truth about herself in her life. Native servants always saled and
submitted to you, whatever you did. She had never thought much about her
looks, but she wondered if she was as unattractive as Ben Weatherstaff and she
also wondered if she looked as sour as he had looked before before the robin
came. She actually began to wonder also if she was "nasty tempered." She felt
uncomfortable. Suddenly a clear rippling little sound broke out near her and she
turned around She was standing a few feet from a young apple tree and the
robin had flown on to one of its branches and had burst out into a scrap
of a song. Ben Weatherstaff laughed outright. "What did he do that for?" asked
Mary. "He's made up his mind to make friends with thee," replied Ben. "Dang me if
he hasn't took a fancy to thee." "To me?"
said Mary, and she moved toward the little tree softly and looked up. "Would
you make friends with me?" she said to the robin just as if she was speaking to a
person. "Would you?" And she did not say it either in her hard little voice or in
her imperious Indian voice, but in a tone so soft and eager and coaxing that Ben
Weatherstaff was as surprised as she had been when she heard him
whistle. "Why," he cried out th said that as nice and human as if that was a real
child instead of a sharp old woman th said it almost like Dickon talks to his
wild things on the mo Do you know Dickon?" Mary asked, turning
around rather in a hurry. "Everybody knows him Dickens wandering about everywhere
the very blackberries and Heather Bells knows him. I warrant the foxes shows him
where their cubs lies and the Skylock doesn't hide their nests from him." Mary
would have liked to ask some more questions She was almost as curious
about Dickon as she was about the deserted garden. But just that moment the
robin, who had ended his song, gave a little shake of his wings, spread them
and flew away. He had made his visit and had other things to
do. "He has flown over the wall!" Mary cried out, watching him. "He has flown into the
orchard— —he has flown across the other wall— —into the garden where there is no
door!" "He lives there," said old Ben. "He came out of the egg there. If he's courau in
he's making up to some young madam of a robin that lives among the old Ro rose trees
there rose trees said Mary. "Are there rose trees Ben Weatherstaff took up his spade
again and began to dig. "There was 10 year' ago," he mumbled. "I should like to see them,"
said Mary. "Where is the green door? There must be a door
somewhere." Ben drove his spade deep and looked as uncompany as he had looked when she first saw
him then There was 10 year' ago, but there isn't now," he said. "No door!" cried Mary.
"There must be." "None as anyone can find and none as is anyone's business. Don't
you be a meddlesome wench and poke your nose where it's no cause to go. Here, I
must go on with my work. Get you gone and play you. I've no more time." And he
actually stopped digging, threw his spade over his shoulder and walked off, without
even glancing at her or saying goodby